[
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of World Wetlands Day 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Wetlands and Climate Change ",
            "Wetlands and Biodiversity ",
            "Wetlands and Water ",
            "Protecting Wetlands for our Common Future "
        ],
        "answer": "Protecting Wetlands for our Common Future ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the maximum amount that banks can charge from customers per transaction after free ATM transaction are over?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 19  ",
            "Rs 20 ",
            "Rs 22 ",
            "Rs 21 "
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 22 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the interchange fee per transaction for financial transactions that banks can charge?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 17 ",
            "Rs 21 ",
            "Rs 19  ",
            "Rs 20 "
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 19  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the interchange fee per transaction for non- financial transactions that banks can charge?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 4 ",
            "Rs 7 ",
            "Rs 6 ",
            "Rs 5 "
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 7 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "CreditAccess Grameen has secured approval for a $50 million commitment from which organisation?",
        "options": [
            "International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) ",
            "International Development Association (IDA) ",
            "International Finance Corporation (IFC) ",
            "Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MIGA) "
        ],
        "answer": "International Finance Corporation (IFC) ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has won the Best New Age Album Award at the 67th Grammy Awards 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Anoushka Shankar ",
            "Chandrika Tandon ",
            "Asha Puthli ",
            "D. Niharika Desai "
        ],
        "answer": "Chandrika Tandon ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the Grammy 2025 award in Record of the Year category?",
        "options": [
            "Beyonc\u00e9 ",
            "Lady Gaga ",
            "Harry Styles ",
            "Kendrick Lamar  "
        ],
        "answer": "Kendrick Lamar  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these has won the Album of the Year award at the Grammy Awards 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Beyonc\u00e9 ",
            "Chilombo ",
            "Black Pumas ",
            "Everyday Life "
        ],
        "answer": "Beyonc\u00e9 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the Gyan Bharatam Mission, recently seen in the news?",
        "options": [
            "To promote online education. ",
            "To conserve India's manuscript heritage. ",
            "To establish new academic institutions across India. ",
            "To preserve India's ancient monuments and heritage sites "
        ],
        "answer": "To conserve India's manuscript heritage. ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding GARBH-INi-DRISHTI:  1. It is a data dashboard that provides a comprehensive overview of one of South Asia\u2019s largest pregnancy cohort datasets.  2. It will help researchers to conduct research which is aimed at improving maternal and neonatal health outcomes.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "\"Ekuverin\" is the joint military exercise between India and which country?",
        "options": [
            "Singapore  ",
            "Malaysia  ",
            "Maldives  ",
            "Indonesia "
        ],
        "answer": "Maldives  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who won the title of the Tata Steel Masters Chess Tournament 2025?",
        "options": [
            "R Praggnanandhaa ",
            "Gukesh D ",
            "Arjun Erigaisi ",
            "Pentala Harikrishna "
        ],
        "answer": "R Praggnanandhaa ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which cricketer has been honoured with the 2023-24 Col.C.K.Nayudu lifetime achievement award by the BCCI (Board of Control for Cricket in India)?",
        "options": [
            "Sachin Tendulkar ",
            "Kapil Dev ",
            "Syed Kirmani ",
            "Anil Kumble "
        ],
        "answer": "Sachin Tendulkar ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been honoured with the 2023-24 BCCI's Polly Umrigar Award for Best International Cricketer?",
        "options": [
            "Ravindra Jadeja ",
            "Hardik Pandya ",
            "Ravichandran Ashwin ",
            "Jasprit Bumrah "
        ],
        "answer": "Jasprit Bumrah ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has been honoured with the 2023-24 BCCI's Best Women International Cricketer award?",
        "options": [
            "Smriti Mandhana ",
            "Mithali Raj ",
            "Deepti Sharma ",
            "Harmanpreet Kaur "
        ],
        "answer": "Smriti Mandhana ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state government has received Nabard's approval for 127 projects worth Rs 903.21 crore, focusing on MLA-priority schemes and rural infrastructure?",
        "options": [
            "Uttar Pradesh  ",
            "Himachal Pradesh  ",
            "Uttarakhand  ",
            "Madhya Pradesh  "
        ],
        "answer": "Himachal Pradesh  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which entity is set to acquire a 25% stake in the US-based fintech startup Seven Technology LLC for \u20b98.7 crore (US$1 million)?",
        "options": [
            "Paytm Cloud Technologies ",
            "Paytm for Business ",
            "Paytm Payments Gateway ",
            "Paytm Credit Cards "
        ],
        "answer": "Paytm Cloud Technologies ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company has unveiled a ChatGPT tool called \"deep research\" ahead of high-level meetings in Tokyo, Japan?",
        "options": [
            "SoluLab ",
            "Neoteric ",
            "Peerbits ",
            "OpenAI "
        ],
        "answer": "OpenAI ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Bandhavgarh Tiger Reserve lies in which state?",
        "options": [
            "Rajasthan ",
            "Odisha ",
            "Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Karnataka  "
        ],
        "answer": "Madhya Pradesh ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Bart De Wever has been appointed the Prime Minister of which country?",
        "options": [
            "Peru  ",
            "Belarus  ",
            "Belgium  ",
            "Malaysia  "
        ],
        "answer": "Belgium  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which Indian state was the country's first White Tiger Breeding Center recently approved?",
        "options": [
            "Odisha ",
            "Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Karnataka ",
            "Rajasthan  "
        ],
        "answer": "Madhya Pradesh ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "When is World Cancer Day observed annually?",
        "options": [
            "2 February ",
            "3 February ",
            "4 February ",
            "5 February  "
        ],
        "answer": "4 February ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which app has been launched by the central government to provide healthcare assistance to Indian Hajj pilgrims?",
        "options": [
            "Hajj Care App ",
            "Hajj Support App ",
            "Hajj Sahayata App ",
            "Hajj Suvidha App  "
        ],
        "answer": "Hajj Suvidha App  ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which institution has launched India\u2019s largest metal 3D printing machine for rocket components?",
        "options": [
            "IIT Madras ",
            "IIT Delhi ",
            "IIT Kanpur ",
            "IIT Hyderabad "
        ],
        "answer": "IIT Hyderabad ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the total export from India in 2023-24?",
        "options": [
            "USD 618.55 billion ",
            "USD 517.39 billion ",
            "USD 818.47 billion ",
            "USD 778.21 billion "
        ],
        "answer": "USD 778.21 billion ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country was the largest buyer of Indian merchandise goods in 2023-24?",
        "options": [
            "USA ",
            "UAE ",
            "UK ",
            "China "
        ],
        "answer": "USA ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country is the largest buyer of Indian-made mobile phones in 2023-24?",
        "options": [
            "United States of America ",
            "China ",
            "Russia  ",
            "Japan "
        ],
        "answer": "United States of America ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the International Big Cat Alliance:  1. It was launched by India during the event \u2018Commemorating 50 years of Project Tiger\u2019.  2. It aims to conserve seven big cats namely -Tiger, Lion, Leopard, Snow Leopard, Cheetah, Jaguar and Puma.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state has appointed a panel to draft the Uniform Civil Code (UCC)?",
        "options": [
            "? ",
            "Rajasthan ",
            "Gujarat ",
            "Maharashtra ",
            "Uttar Pradesh "
        ],
        "answer": "Rajasthan ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country will host the BRICS Youth Entrepreneurship Meeting in March 2025?",
        "options": [
            "India ",
            "Brazil ",
            "China ",
            "South Africa "
        ],
        "answer": "India ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which African country became the first to eliminate onchocerciasis?",
        "options": [
            "Nigeria ",
            "Niger ",
            "Ethiopia ",
            "Kenya "
        ],
        "answer": "Niger ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "By what percentage has India's tiger population increased over the past two decades?",
        "options": [
            "20% ",
            "25% ",
            "30% ",
            "35% "
        ],
        "answer": "30% ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "The phrase \"Satyameva Jayate\" is derived from which of the following texts?",
        "options": [
            "Bhagavad Gita ",
            "Rigveda ",
            "Mundaka Upanishad ",
            "Ramayana "
        ],
        "answer": "Mundaka Upanishad ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the Gaia Mission, recently seen in the news:  1. It is NASA\u2019s astronomical observatory mission.  2. It aims to create the largest, most precise three-dimensional map of the Milky Way galaxy.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "2 only ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the Extremely Large Telescope (ELT), recently seen in the news:  1. It will be the world's largest optical telescope.  2. It is being built by the European Southern Observatory (ESO) in Chile.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "Both 1 and 2 ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the National Youth Parliament Scheme 2.0:  1. It will strengthen the roots of democracy and tolerance of the views of others.  2. Under this scheme only individuals can participate in the Youth Parliament programme.  Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
            "1 only ",
            "2 only ",
            "Both 1 and 2 ",
            "Neither 1 nor 2 "
        ],
        "answer": "1 only ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the current unemployment rate in the country as per the latest Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS)?",
        "options": [
            "6.1% ",
            "4.5% ",
            "3.8% ",
            "3.2% "
        ],
        "answer": "3.2% ",
        "source": "Unknown"
    }
]